We're now at the part of our conversation
where I can answer the
question we started off with,
which is, why do you breathe?
And we talked about how,
eh, it's oxygen and we need that.
Well, oxygen is not really
a fuel for metabolism.
It's needed to go through
aerobic metabolism,
but the fuel is coming from
your fat and carbohydrates.
I only need oxygen during
aerobic metabolism,
but I'm very effective at anaerobic,
which means I can produce energy
without the need of oxygen.
But to finish those processes,
I've got to have the oxygen around.
And so it's a little bit of a twist here.
This is also explaining
why even if you're an anaerobic athlete,
you still care deeply
about your aerobic system
because this is what
allows you to recover,
to completely metabolize
your carbohydrates,
to finish that process
and restore yourself
back to homeostasis.
The faster you can do that,
the faster you can repeat
your anaerobic processes.
You can recover, you can
get back to training,
get back to competition.
The more you practice, the better you get,
the better you perform.
And so what's actually
fully happening is this.
When you take a breath in and you inhale,
you're bringing in amongst other things,
but primarily oxygen.
When you take a breath out,
you're breathing out CO2.
The oxygen you bring in is primarily there
to regulate metabolic processes.
But the CO2 you're exhaling
is regulating your pH.
Now there's a handful of things
your body will regulate
almost anything else.
One of them is your pH.
It does not like to mess with this.
If you were to look at other markers
like say your blood glucose,
you realize that that's highly variable.
It can be as low as, you know,
70 milligrams per deciliter,
as high as 150 during exercise
or something like that.
And so you can see it all double
or maybe even triple
the amount in the blood.
You would never do that with pH.
It has an extremely tight window
that it will not move out of.
And that's because all the
enzymes that are required
for you to go through
any metabolic process
need to be in a certain pH range.
If it gets out of that,
it becomes too acidic or too alkalotic.
They can't function,
you can't create energy.
You're going to die very, very quickly.
So pH is insanely important
to hold into a tight window.
And so what happens is
you don't feel that air hunger
or that desire to breathe
because oxygen starts getting low.
Remember, especially at rest
or even during exercise,
you can produce energy anaerobically.
So when you start getting low on oxygen,
you'll just switch to
anaerobic metabolism.
It's not necessarily a reason
for you to panic, to stress,
or to change your behavior.
Increases in CO2 though will do that.
And so remember your muscle is,
whether it's using fat as a
fuel or carbohydrates as a fuel,
it's trying to generate
a molecule called ATP.
This is the energy
currency in all of biology.
And it doesn't matter what you
use that ATP for by the way.
It doesn't matter if we're
talking about skeletal muscle,
we're talking about cardiac
muscle or anything else.
So whether you're using this for exercise
to power your brain to
recover, to digest food,
it's irrelevant here, right?
We're going to use
carbohydrates or fat as a fuel,
we're going to make ATP.
And then at the end,
the final byproduct of all
metabolism is going to be
water, CO2, and ATP.
So the CO2 concentration increases
as metabolic rate increases.
As a result of that,
you start then moving CO2 from
your tissue into the blood.
Concentrations of CO2
then and blood go up.
You've got chemoreceptors
in your brainstem and various other places
that are going to be
paying extreme attention
to the amount of CO2 in your blood.
If CO2 gets really, really high,
we call this hypercapnia.
If it gets low, it's called hypocapnia.
Remember those terms.
So hypercapnia increases
in CO2 concentration
actually signal your red blood cells
to drop the oxygen on them,
making it easier for your muscle
to extract and absorb the oxygen.
Effectively you think about it this way.
If CO2 is high in the blood,
your body is under the assumption
you're going through a lot of metabolism,
so it's under the assumption
that we want to use
and need a lot of oxygen.
So it reduces that affinity.
And this is called the Bohr effect.
If you get hypocapnic,
again too low of CO2,
it does the opposite.
Now this is going to be counterintuitive
when we talk about
things like CO2 tolerance
and respiratory rate in future episodes
as to why you could
potentially have problems
with hyperventilation or over-breathing.
So what's happening in this context is
those signals are being sent to your brain
and that is interpreting it as saying
CO2 is too high, let's reduce that.
The way you reduce CO2
concentrations in your blood
is to exhale.
And so this would cause you
to increase your respiratory rate
and to start either mildly or
excessively hyperventilating.
And this is why as you
exercise your respiratory rate,
again the amount of breaths
you're taking, goes up.
It is in part to increase and
bring in oxygen, of course.
But when we're doing it anaerobically,
we're not using oxygen anyways.
So the real reason we're breathing so hard
and we're panting,
[Andy breathing deeply]
and all that stuff
as we're getting harder and
harder of our exercise is
because we're trying to dump
and get rid of all that CO2 buildup.
Remember, excess CO2 is altering pH.
This is making us more acidic.
This becomes an extreme problem.
And so another way to think about this is,
when you inhale, that's
actually a sympathetic driver.
And so your heart rate
increases during inhalation.
When you exhale, it is
parasympathetic and it drops.
So effectively what's
happening is your body is
sort of saying, oh, you're inhaling,
we're assuming then
you're bringing in oxygen.
Let's get prepared to deliver this oxygen
throughout the system.
When you're exhaling, it's the opposite.
I don't want to be in a situation
where I'm hyperventilating.
I don't need to be breathing
too much because if again,
that CO2 gets too low,
instead of being acidic,
we are now in respiratory alkalosis.
So the opposite direction, right?
We're too basic.
And so it slows the heart rate down.
So every time you take a breath in,
your heart rate jumps up a little bit.
Every time you take a breath
out, it goes down a little bit.
So if I'm altering my respiratory rate,
I'm then altering my heart rate.
And this is why things like
HRV are so intrinsically tied
to things like respiratory rate.
I can't let us move off this point
without saying one final thing.
I know we want to get to our
three Is here in one second.
But a lot of people are aware,
and in the coaching world,
people use HRV very often,
and there's a lot of data to support this.
There's a lot of critical
information we can get
for assessing, say,
exercise volume, fatigue,
readiness, and things like that.
Tons of value there.
But I don't think enough
people are paying attention
to respiratory rate.
This is really highlighted
in a paper that just came
out in the last few months,
and so I'd like to bring
this to your attention.
What they did is looked
at college-aged students
and they simply measured
their respiratory rate.
And one of the things that they
found that's interesting is
for every breath per minute that increase,
so if a respiratory rate went
from 15 breaths per minute
to 16 breaths per minute,
they increased their likelihood
of experiencing stress
by 1.25X.
And what I found particularly
interesting about this is
they found that irrespective
of changes in things like HRV,
total hours of sleep, sleep
efficiency, sleep onset,
and various other things
that are typically
the metrics used to measure overall stress
and autonomic nervous system functionality
and things like that.
And so what we're going
over here is not to say
that HRV or sleep are
not good metrics to take,
they clearly are.
It's just that you're going to find things
in the respiratory rate
that you're not necessarily
going to see in other places
that give you great clues
about overall stress.
So strongly encourage you
to pay attention to respiratory rate.
And we'll talk about that
plenty in the future.
[music]